<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collyrium a sermon of destructive ignorance and saving knowledge, preached in Christ-Church, Dublin, August 4, 1672, and published at the importunity of divers, who thought it might tend to disabuse many well-meaning people / by Edw. Wetenhall.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10581652</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10581652</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1391:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Collyrium a sermon of destructive ignorance and saving knowledge, preached in Christ-Church, Dublin, August 4, 1672, and published at the importunity of divers, who thought it might tend to disabuse many well-meaning people / by Edw. Wetenhall.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Rooks, and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Collyrium.</p>
            <p>A SERMON OF Deſtructive Ignorance, AND Saving Knowledge.</p>
            <p>Preached in <hi>Chriſt-Church, Dublin, Auguſt</hi> 4. 1672.</p>
            <p>And Publiſhed at the importunity of divers, who thought it might tend to diſabuſe many well-meaning people.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edw. Wetenhall,</hi> B. D. Prebendary of St. <hi>Peters Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Rooks,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet, Dublin.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reverend Father in God, MICHAEL Lord Archbishop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> AND Lord Chancellor of the Kingdom of <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DIvers of my Friends, Auditors of this Sermon, have taken occaſion to be ſo troubleſome to me for it, that I ſaw no way to deliver my ſelf from their diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but by gratifying their importunity. The ſame Perſons, as I underſtood, expreſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing when they ſhould have a Copy they would make it publick, I reſolved by making the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſuch my ſelf, to give both them and the World leave to take as much of it as they
<pb facs="tcp:45271:3"/> ſhould liſt. Being now publick, it comes, as Duty directs it, an humble Preſent unto your Grace.</p>
            <p>I am not at all ſolicitous as to its Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the World: being conſcious to my ſelf its Contents are wholly ſober truth, with which if any ſhould be angry, I am not yet ſatisfied that I ought to be concerned thereat, otherwiſe than to vouchſafe ſuch perſons my Pity, and the charity of my Prayers.</p>
            <p>I only fear how your Grace may reſent ſo bold a Dedication: But I have to ſay for my ſelf, That, by the laxeſt Laws of Gratitude, I ought ſome publick teſtification of your Graces ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Sweetneſs and Conſtancy to me; That I had no fitter means of ſuch teſtification than this, this being my firſt appearance in publick in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and beſides it being not poſſible for me ever to preſent in ſo ſhort a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, more of my ſelf and moſt intimate thoughts in a caſe of this nature, than I have done here: (Now Firſt-fruits, and what is moſt ſincerely Ours, uſe to come moſt acceptable Oblations.)
<pb facs="tcp:45271:3"/> That the Experience, which I have had of your Graces favourable admiſſion of Addreſſes far more troubleſome than this, gave me confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence an attempt of Gratitude would not be ill taken.</p>
            <p>In this confidence I forbear other Apologies, and moſt paſſionately pray to your Grace, amidſt the great and various Viciſſitudes of Humane affairs, ſuch continuance of Health, Fortunes, and the Divine Bleſſing, that you may long live, what admirably you are, a glorious Precedent and Patron of all Learning, Worth and Virtue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt Humble Servant, Edw. Wetenhall.</signed>
               <dateline>Dublin, <date>Aug. 13. 1672</date>.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45271:4"/>
            <head>Collyrium: OR, A SERMON
<list>
                  <label>Of</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>Deſtructive Ignorance,</item>
                        <item>Saving Knowledge.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text.</bibl>
               <q>Hoſ. 4. 6. <hi>My people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is a <hi>Rule</hi> as wholſom as general, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving immediately from the great deſign of all Sacred Scripture, (wherein whatſoever was recorded, the Apoſtle aſſures us to have been <hi>written for our enſample</hi> and inſtruction) that in thoſe <hi>ſeveral parts</hi> of it which were on <hi>particular occaſions</hi> more immediately addreſs'd to particular ages,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45271:5"/> peoples or perſons, we ſhould all, as every ſubject is juſtly applicable, <hi>accommodate</hi> it each to our <hi>preſent caſe</hi> and <hi>ſtite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>compliance</hi> with which <hi>Rule,</hi> we ſhall not now concern our ſelves in a curious inqueſt into the Manners and Condition of this Jewiſh age, to whom our Prophet directs his ſpeech<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which (briefly) were ſufficiently corrupt and deplorable; nor yet into the Originals of ſuch their corruption and miſery, (for thoſe matters, though of good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to other purpoſes, than thoſe we have propoſed our ſelves at preſent, are notwithſtanding ſuch, for the not knowing whereof, we are ſecure enough <hi>people</hi> ſhall not be <hi>deſtroyed</hi>)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But rather, taking the boldneſs to ſuppoſe, that what God here <hi>complains</hi> of theſe <hi>Jews</hi> is without injury to the words or us, <hi>accommodable</hi> to our generation; and that even in this <hi>knowing,</hi> and (as preſum'd) moſt Eagle-ey'd <hi>age,</hi> men amongſt us do ſtill <hi>periſh for lack of knowledge,</hi> Firſt, we will direct a ſcrutiny to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the diſcovering <hi>what knowledge</hi> that is, <hi>for lack of</hi> which people amongſt us <hi>are deſtroyed:</hi> and, Secondly, endeavour ſome probable notices, whence thoſe clouds ariſe which obſcure our light, and what the <hi>malignant cauſes</hi> are of the preſent <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive ignorance:</hi> and, Laſtly, with all due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion conſult, what are the moſt hopefull reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be applyed in this caſe.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of all which, we <hi>promiſe,</hi> what we ſay ſhal obſerve due <hi>reverence</hi> to all who have but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45271:5"/> any fair pretence to knowledge, much more to the truly Judicious: and as to thoſe, whoſe good <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> of themſelves are chiefly placed upon their own <hi>confidence,</hi> we <hi>beſeech</hi> ſuch, with all humility, and in the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> that they will be pleaſed to think ſome men in the World, who do little elſe but ſeek knowledge, may have ſome knowledge beſides themſelves; and therefore <hi>impartially</hi> to <hi>conſider,</hi> whether what ſhall be ſaid to them, carry not greater reaſon to convince them of the <hi>lack</hi> of <hi>ſound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> than what their own ſtrong preſumptions bear, to enſure them of their being already maſters of it. No <hi>wiſe</hi> man but will be <hi>thankfull</hi> to be <hi>ſhewed</hi> his <hi>error:</hi> none therefore, who pretend to be ſuch, may reaſonably ill reſent, what ſincerity and good will ſpeaks, to diſcover ſuch miſtakes, which there is much better evidence to pronounce pernicious, than to imagine tolerable.</p>
            <p>And that it may be apparent. I intend not to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> the age by a wild and indefinite imputation of ignorance to it, I ſhall with all candour own the knowledge in which our age may be confeſſed emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; and therefore, <hi>firſt,</hi> bring in a <hi>negative</hi> anſwer to the propoſed matter of enquiry, by ſaying, that people are not deſtroyed at preſent,</p>
            <p>1. For lack of a <hi>Dogmatick knowledge,</hi> amounting from intricate ſpeculations, and fine notions, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther newly coined or retrieved from their deſerved Graves. We have both in <hi>Sacred matters</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> conceits enough to ſpare the World, very ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45271:6"/> to furniſh (I had almoſt ſaid to overlay) it, ſhould it continue to well nigh infinite ſucceſſions of ages. Beſides that we have been fertile of ſome <hi>Opinions</hi> which our days may <hi>ſolely</hi> boaſt of, there are few <hi>old Hereſies,</hi> which have not received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us what <hi>improvement</hi> miſchievous wits could give them. And when the preſent <hi>new-faſhioned ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities</hi> ſhall grow <hi>ſtale,</hi> we are not likely to want a freſh ſucceſſion, ſo long as <hi>Spiritual illuminations</hi> are ſo frequent, and every petite hit of wild imagination muſt be reputed an irradiation of the Holy Ghoſt, and a New Light from above.</p>
            <p>Nor doth this eminency extend it ſelf only to <hi>ſingle Opinions;</hi> but, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> we are generally skilfull in Bodies and <hi>Syſtems</hi> of them; and thoſe <hi>modell'd</hi> and contrived into a dutifull ſubſerviency to the common <hi>deſigns</hi> of innovating <hi>Factions.</hi> Of all which new-framed <hi>Schemes,</hi> this be ſure is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Law, that they be <hi>lax</hi> enough, immediately to place, upon none or eaſie terms, all who <hi>receive</hi> them in an inamiſſible poſſeſſion of the Divine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; and <hi>rigid</hi> enough on the other ſide to damn all, who are ſuch Infidels as to put a <hi>difference</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Saints and Confidents, or to think mens Chriſtianity ought to have other reaſon beſides their own preſumption.</p>
            <p>And from theſe two ariſeth a <hi>third</hi> ſort of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious knowledge,</hi> in which we are of ſo high attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that all our predeceſſors whereſoever, have been but meer Punies and Chits in compariſon of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45271:6"/> us. I know not by what name fitlier to ſtile it, than <hi>Theological Lullianiſme,</hi> or the art of ſenceleſs Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity-Harangues: a fine verboſe talkative skill, by which men are able, without the trouble of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, to deliver endleſs and unintelligible Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in the language of the Times, to <hi>preach</hi> and <hi>pray moſt ſpiritually,</hi> but in truth to amuſe and confound themſelves and their weak admirers with neither knows what.</p>
            <p>I would not here be miſtaken, as if I did ſlight the <hi>gifts</hi> of <hi>utterance</hi> in a particular relation as well to <hi>prayer,</hi> as <hi>preaching,</hi> in <hi>places</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons</hi> where their uſe is meet: But I would fain have men rationally to conceive of them. For verily it is neceſſary, that as we put a difference between ſpeaking <hi>ſpiritually</hi> and ſpeaking <hi>much,</hi> ſo that we know even <hi>ready</hi> ſpeaking is a <hi>habit</hi> attained by the common bleſſing of God upon mens <hi>natural parts, induſtry</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> in ſome meaſure improving them; and no ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>inſpiration</hi> as fancied: much leſs doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute that which they call <hi>Saving knowledge,</hi> or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily proceed from a ſanctified heart. And that therefore the affectation of many and new-coined forms of ſpeech ought not to be ſo idolized, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not at all an extraordinary gift; And further, in as much as nothing can be more notorious, than that through this one <hi>Enthuſiaſtical</hi> ſtrain of thus <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>praying,</hi> a multitude of the moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pretenders to Religion are run clearly beyond all <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>ſobriety,</hi> and never now think they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45271:7"/> edifie by any Sermon or Prayer, but when they have got a long headleſs piece of ſtuff together, made up of odd Phraſes and canting: Allegories, out of which neither themſelves nor the wit of man can pick ſenſe. That only, I ſay, they judge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to profit by, of which diſtinctly they can make nothing, and which is in truth only a new kind of empty noiſe, and train of riddles void of ſober ſignification.</p>
            <p>I hope it will be obſerved my diſcourſe hitherto hath confin'd it-ſelf to <hi>Religious knowledge:</hi> I could have given an account of other forts of knowledge for lack of which men are not likely to periſh. And I can ſcarcely forbear that marvellous skill and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity we have all attained to in <hi>Politicks,</hi> ſcarce a <hi>Foreman</hi> of a Shop but is acquainted with all the reaſons of <hi>State,</hi> and publick neceſſities, and ſole ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients to ſalve them. And there are here and there diſpers'd little ſmart precocious ſuckers of the late <hi>Republican Bramble,</hi> who ſet up for Maſters in this Myſtery, and ſcrape together Intelligences from every Poſts News, and make up their reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and thence inferr moſt neceſſary and fallible Aphoriſms, which they confidently diſperſe in all Companies, hoping for, what not rarely they find, <hi>greedy admirers,</hi> who giddily lick up all this their Spittle, and as giddily again diffuſe it. But I will paſs this: And of all the knowledge I have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpoke of, I ſay, men are ſo far from being in danger for the lack of a <hi>curious, Dogmatick, verboſe,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45271:7"/> or <hi>pragmatical</hi> knowledge, that I pray God the generality of people be not <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by its <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come then to a <hi>poſitive</hi> ſatisfaction to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry in hand; which I moſt paſſionately beſeech all to attend unto without prejudice, my deſign (God knows it) being only to <hi>undeceive</hi> all I can, to <hi>expoſe</hi> none.</p>
            <p>The knowledge for lack of which people at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are deſtroyed, is <hi>a ſober information</hi> of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence touching matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to their real happineſs: What thoſe matters are univerſally to <hi>all</hi> men, it is not <hi>eaſie,</hi> haply not <hi>poſſible</hi> preciſely to determine; by reaſon of the <hi>variety</hi> of mens conditions, and the anſwerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Juſtice, according to that moſt equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table rule, (<hi>Luke 12. 48.) Unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall much be required.</hi> Certainly <hi>leſs</hi> than this can be required of no man of <hi>ordinary</hi> reaſon and condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he underſtand his <hi>happineſs</hi> conſiſts not in any of thoſe lower enjoyments, but that as his Soul is an intelligent and immortal being, ſo it can never be ſatisfied but with that which hath within it, what ſuits and may perfect all its powers, and ſhall be eternal as it ſelf, of which Nature is nothing here below. Only <hi>Virtue</hi> here adminiſters any thing of real and durable <hi>content.</hi> And if <hi>perfect Virtue</hi> could be attained, and we eternally ſecured therein, free from all moleſtation and trouble conſequent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45271:8"/> upon former guilt, thence muſt needs reſult a <hi>full content</hi> and complacence, as to any thing from <hi>within</hi> the mans ſelf. And as to what <hi>without</hi> him his Soul could further covet, it being ſuppoſed that in <hi>God</hi> infinitely dwells all good, and that <hi>Heaven</hi> gives us the ſight and <hi>enjoyment</hi> of him, it cannot be but a perſon ſo qualified as before, being received into Heaven, is compleatly happy, or as bleſſed as he can be. Now to <hi>ſecure</hi> us in perfect Virtue and ſuch its reſult, to acquit us from our Vices, and poſſeſs us eternally of Heaven and the ſight of God, there is no probable (at leaſt no ſafe) way but what <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> propounds.</p>
            <p>Upon this, <hi>Secondly,</hi> follows the neceſſity of <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, or an expectation of remiſſion of ſins and ſuch compleat happineſs through him, upon the performance of the <hi>conditions</hi> he requires. Of which conditions the <hi>ſumme</hi> is, that we believe and honeſtly receive whatſoever was delivered or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by him, when it is ſufficiently declared unto us that it was by him delivered. So that it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that though for the <hi>general,</hi> Faith in Chriſt be the <hi>ſame</hi> to all men, that is to ſay, that all men are bound to receive whatever they are reaſonably ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to have been deliver'd by Chriſt, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore generally to be Virtuous;) yet to <hi>particular</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons it may be <hi>different,</hi> according to the particular degrees of <hi>light</hi> that every one hath enjoyed, that is, according to the evidence or means of ſatisfaction he hath had, and the capableneſs of his mind to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45271:8"/> admit ſuch evidence: ſo that in fine, that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar may be a point of Faith, and ſo of Duty to one man, which to another by reaſon of his ignorance or other impediment is not ſuch. In the mean while this cannot but be indubitably evident to <hi>all</hi> men, who have ſo much as well <hi>heard</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that it requireth all men every where to <hi>repent, Acts</hi> 17. 30.</p>
            <p>That therefore, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> muſt be concluded, that <hi>Repentance from dead works</hi> is a matter of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible neceſſity to the happineſs of every man, that whoſo is not duly informed in the nature of it, may be <hi>deſtroyed for lack of knowledge.</hi> And by ſuch Repentance we are not to underſtand ſome tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient diſpleaſure with our ſelves for ſome actions of ours, which we apprehend to have been imprudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or incommodiouſly done, nor meerly a ſorrow for all our paſt ſins as well known as unknown; But beſides this, (<hi>firſt</hi>) a conſiderate and <hi>ſtedfaſt purpoſe</hi> or reſolvedneſs to forſake ſin, and approve a mans ſelf impartially holy, which is a <hi>change of mind;</hi> and (<hi>ſecondly</hi>) an <hi>honeſt endeavour</hi> according to that reſolvedneſs, which is a <hi>change of life.</hi> Acts of <hi>Contrition, Confeſſion,</hi> and mourning over ſin, are more truly <hi>ſteps</hi> and preparatives to <hi>Repentance,</hi> by which as by a proper cauſe this purpoſe comes to be rooted and ſetled in the mans mind, than Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance it ſelf; which, I ſay, if we will ſpeak of as it is acceptable to God, and available to our ſalvation, we muſt determine to be ſuch a permanent habit as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45271:9"/> already declared, a <hi>new ſtate,</hi> a durable courſe of Reformation, not an act of ſorrow, or a pang of devotion, or an amendment for a day or two. And it is much to be feared, that the want of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this the true nature of Repentance, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by ſome inſufficient Teachers miſtaking, and ſo miſ-repreſenting its notion, has deſtroyed many, and to this day retains the ſame miſchievous and damning influence.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>laſtly,</hi> becauſe we have determined him only to be the true penitent, who thus is, and remains a changed man, that is to ſay, Virtuous according to his reſolves, therefore moſt neceſſary to ſalvation muſt be the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>particular Virtues,</hi> what thoſe Moral Duties are which are required of us, and what thoſe <hi>ſins</hi> which under the pain of eternal wrath we are to avoid. Namely, that to <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>outward worſhip</hi> of Prayer, Sacraments, and attending his Word, we owe a <hi>devout</hi> and pious <hi>temper</hi> of Soul, conſiſting in a ſweet combination of <hi>Faith, Hope, Love, Humility, Fear,</hi> and what Graces elſe of the like nature: to Men, if <hi>Governours, Honour, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> adhaeſion as need ſhall require. He's no good Chriſtian who would not venture his Life and Fortunes, if called thereto, in defence of his rightfull Soveraign. Again, to men if <hi>ſimply Superiors,</hi> and having nothing of obligation upon us, but what the eminency of their condition gives them, yet even to theſe reſpectively according to their degree, <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reverence.</hi> To <hi>Equals,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45271:9"/> due <hi>valuation</hi> of them, and modeſt <hi>praeference:</hi> to <hi>Inferiors, courteſie</hi> and condeſcention as need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: to <hi>all, juſtice, charity,</hi> and <hi>good will,</hi> as well in words and actions as in thought. And, laſtly, to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> a <hi>care</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> ſuiting our nature and condition, in not betraying our reaſon, our health, our honour, our eſtate, by any intemperate, vile or pittiful practices. I do not ſay that every private Chriſtian muſt be an exquiſite Caſuiſt, or able to cleave an hair in determining the right of matters in every perplexed caſe: Herein they have Spiritual Guides appointed them by God, whom they are to conſult. But ſurely as to the <hi>ordinary caſes</hi> of life, of common concernment to all men, each perſon ought to wear knowledge enough about him, to determine what is his <hi>duty,</hi> what his <hi>ſin,</hi> or he is in great danger of being <hi>deſtroyed for lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe points then, the <hi>true happineſs</hi> of man, and (the means thereto) <hi>Faith</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, and <hi>Repentance</hi> from dead works, and to that purpoſe the <hi>nature</hi> of particular <hi>Virtues,</hi> we have ſaid it is neceſſary the Conſcience be ſoberly informed, or that in default thereof, men are in all likelihood of <hi>periſhing for lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what we mean by <hi>due information</hi> of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> will appear beſt by conſidering the nature of Conſcience it ſelf, which in truth is but another name for the Underſtanding, conſidered in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular regard. At leaſt as the mind of man takes in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45271:10"/> or conceives the natures and notions of things, and generally judgeth of them, we call it the <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:</hi> As it is furniſhed with certain principles and rules, by which as by its next and moſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate guide the mans practice is directed, we call it <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Now that any thing may become a <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> of Conſcience, and ſo be of force to ſway a man in his practice, it is neceſſary that the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which is ſuppoſed a Principle, be not only <hi>underſtood</hi> but <hi>believed,</hi> more or leſs, according as more ſtrongly or faintly it ſways the man. So that for a mans Conſcience to be duly informed touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe matters, is not only for him ſpeculatively to comprehend the meaning of ſuch Propoſitions as theſe, God is the chief good and happineſs of man, Faith, Repentance and Virtue, are the means to attain the enjoyme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this God, but to be deeply in his heart convinced and perſwaded of the verity of theſe things, and his concernment as to them.</p>
            <p>If therefore any perſon amongſt us, of common reaſon and capacity, be <hi>ignorant</hi> wherein true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs doth conſiſt, what the true nature of Faith in Chriſt, Repentance, of Devotion, Juſtice, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Temperance, and Chaſtity is, or further, <hi>want</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of ſuch things as are <hi>ſufficient to perſwade</hi> him of the truth and neceſſity of theſe points, I ſay, that ſuch perſon dying thus ignorant, in all likelihood periſheth for <hi>lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45271:10"/>
            <p>But when I ſay thus, I would be underſtood to ſpeak only of ſuch whom providence hath bleſſed with the good tidings of the Goſpel of Peace, and abilities in a good meaſure to comprehend its Doctrine: That, of the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, and of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals,</hi> to whom leſs hath been given, leſs will be required, I ſuppoſe it becometh not me to doubt. He amongſt ſuch, who <hi>believeth</hi> God to <hi>be,</hi> and to <hi>be a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> if he ſhall ſo <hi>ſeek</hi> him, and yet believe little or nothing more, becauſe by ſeeking he can find no more, may, for ought I know, ſit above them in Heaven, who for want of unbyaſs'd <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> as well to Almighty God, as the poor virtuous Ethnick, or weak headed Innocent, judge the <hi>men</hi> ſo bad, as to be unfit for Heaven; or <hi>God</hi> ſo ill-natur'd, that is the infinitely good, ſo mercileſs a Tyrant, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude men from happineſs, for what he deſignedly left them under an utter diſability to redreſs.</p>
            <p>And now we are thus far up the hill, and can take a proſpect of the <hi>deſtructive ignorance,</hi> let us ſtand ſtill a while and look back, and ſee if we have not a reaſon to take up a <hi>lamentation,</hi> that black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enfolds large tracts, and <hi>multitudes</hi> periſh <hi>for lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meekly and without an affront to the knowledge of the age, <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to that knowledge which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a <hi>ſober</hi> and diſtinct <hi>underſtanding</hi> Divine <hi>Truths,</hi> even ſuch as are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> are not the generality much to ſeek? It hath not been the buſineſs of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45271:11"/> many Teachers to inſtruct, but amuſe people in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. We have been many of us bred up with Seraphick diſcourſes of the <hi>in-dwelling</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and of <hi>wonder-working Grace,</hi> and of the <hi>Elect</hi> of God from <hi>before the foundation of the World;</hi> with <hi>endleſs</hi> and impertinent (many times moſt <hi>ſeditious</hi> and lying) catalogues of the <hi>ſigns of the Grace</hi> of God in his people: With the <hi>glympſes of Chriſt,</hi> and how <hi>Believers</hi> are made <hi>partakers</hi> of the Divine Nature, whether the <hi>eſſence</hi> of it be in us, or only its <hi>effects,</hi> (which laſt was too ſober a truth for the age:) How each <hi>Believer</hi> ought to ſeek after a <hi>diſtinct com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with <hi>each perſon</hi> of the Trinity by himſelf; with a multitude of ſuch <hi>myſterious whimſies,</hi> out of which, as I ſaid, the wit and reaſon of man cannot pick ſober ſence or truth. Hence it came to paſs, that every amuſed or <hi>affrighted</hi> and thunder-ſtruck perſon, finding within his breaſt a <hi>change</hi> which he knew not what to make of, in truth a <hi>tumult</hi> of <hi>affections</hi> much like (what they lead unto) a <hi>phrenſie,</hi> (ſometimes <hi>wonder,</hi> anon <hi>fear,</hi> then <hi>hope,</hi> then <hi>joy</hi>) every ſuch perſon, I ſay, thought himſelf a <hi>Convert,</hi> and began to talk of his <hi>experience.</hi> And this was the <hi>work of Grace</hi> and <hi>Converſion.</hi> Then every one, who could perſwade himſelf God had a favour from ever for him, and not for another, had the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Gods Elect,</hi> and this was <hi>Believing.</hi> Every <hi>good-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Woman,</hi> who by ſympathizing with groans and whynings which ſhe heard from the Pulpit, put finger into the eye and <hi>cryed,</hi> was a <hi>broken-hearted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45271:11"/> perſon,</hi> and this was <hi>Repentance.</hi> And in every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany without fear or wit to <hi>talk</hi> of <hi>Sermons,</hi> and <hi>Gods people,</hi> and to look <hi>demurely,</hi> was to be <hi>a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> and <hi>precious</hi> perſon. And this was <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> And, alas! theſe miſtakes are ſo deeply rooted in the hearts of many of the common people, of <hi>honeſt good-meaning,</hi> that we who would redreſs them, coming upon this ſad diſadvantage, that we are to put people out of conceit with themſelves, and what they have a long time pleaſed themſelves in, as in a Fools Paradiſe, are by many ſuch honeſt abuſed perſons diſreliſh'd, reviled, cryed out on as <hi>Carnal Preachers,</hi> no whit ſpiritualized; nor can it yet (God knows when it will) be effected, that the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>multitude</hi> be much more than a confident, preſumptuous and irrational <hi>humour,</hi> than which there being nothing more contrary to ſober knowledge, alas! people <hi>periſh for lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> as to <hi>Divine knowledge,</hi> as <hi>oppoſed</hi> to <hi>Scepticiſme</hi> in Religion, and as it ſignifies the ſeeing the evidence of Religious Principles, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades us ſolidly of their truth, is not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint as juſt and ſad as of the former branch, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes periſh for lack of it? As generally, <hi>juſtifying Faith,</hi> amongſt people, is nothing but a truſt or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of Gods favour</hi> in Chriſt, ſo, with the moſt part, the <hi>Faith of Principles</hi> is little more than <hi>Opinion,</hi> inſomuch that not only the <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Creed,</hi> that is, the chief points of Chriſtian Religion, but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45271:12"/> even the common principles of <hi>all Religion,</hi> the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boundaries of good and evil, are <hi>doubted,</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd and impugned, and by reaſon of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Diſputants,</hi> we can ſcarce find <hi>Believers.</hi> Of this, ſaid experience being an irrefragable proof, is there not reaſon to take it up for a <hi>lamentation,</hi> Alas! for it is <hi>a day of darkneſs and of gloomineſs, a day of clouds and thick darkneſs ſpread upon the face</hi> not of the <hi>valleys</hi> only, but of the <hi>mountains?</hi> The <hi>ignorance</hi> (or which is much the ſame, <hi>miſtake</hi>) of theſe plain <hi>neceſſaries</hi> in Religion, the not-ſeeing, or (which is but a willful blindneſs) not-attending to the evidences which would perſwade men touching them, <hi>deſtroys</hi> many not only of the <hi>inferiour</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, but <hi>higher</hi> Perſonages.</p>
            <p>But we have poſſibly dwelt too long on the view of this ungratefull ſubject, the common <hi>deſtructive crime</hi> and woe: and time it were to conſult its <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,</hi> were it not proper and naturally conducing thereunto, firſt to inſpect its <hi>Cauſes,</hi> which was the ſecond thing propounded.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> of which I take to be, the <hi>making</hi> ſo <hi>many</hi> things <hi>neceſſary</hi> to Chriſtianity, which indeed are not: for from hence it comes to paſs, that moſt men being not able to give their whole time to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and commonly allowing to it only ſome odd parts of their vacancy and leiſure, can never pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate and digeſt the ſo manifold points and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of its enlarged body. And then in ſo great a <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> of pretended neceſſaries, not being able
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45271:12"/> to <hi>diſcern</hi> what are <hi>principally</hi> (and it may be truly and ſolely) <hi>neceſſary,</hi> they ſtick upon the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular and commonly ventilated points, and totally or for the moſt part neglect what to them is of greater concernment. Verily, were <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſuch an <hi>infinite thing</hi> as ſome ſeem to have made it, it is not moſt mens <hi>lives,</hi> (conſidering they muſt follow common Callings) that were ſufficient for them to attain unto a mean knowledge therein.</p>
            <p>Amongſt thoſe things made neceſſary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, which are not, I ſhall inſtance only in two heads; Various <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and Various <hi>Gifts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, It is ſcarce a moderate <hi>Volume</hi> which will contain a <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> as ſome of our Faith-menders have enlarged it. And yet we have all heard of more Holy and Orthodox times, when <hi>Twelve Articles</hi> compriſed its ſumme. If we would have more, we have a <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> which <hi>firſt</hi> acquaints us with our Baptiſmal Vow, or the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant every of us made or ought to keep with God; then, briefly, explains the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and Decalogue, things we are concerned to know by the particular branches of that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Vow or Covenant. And then, laſtly, adds what is further neceſſary to be known and obſerved by us, as to the Seals of that Covenant. This was thought <hi>enough</hi> by our Church for <hi>common</hi> men to know, in order to the making them Chriſtians, and poſſibly was more than what the Primitive Church for two or three hundred years thought neceſſary too.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:45271:13"/>
            <p>What will ſome ſay? will you then have our <hi>Bibles</hi> taken from us? By no means: for theſe will teach you the ſame things in different forms, and beſides convince you of their truth, and otherwiſe affect you with them. But when plain perſons meet with <hi>hard places</hi> in their Bibles, not relating to theſe neceſſaries, I would have them paſs ſuch difficulties over, and not interpret them on their own heads, without a due Teacher, but content themſelves commonly to know, to believe, be affected with, and practiſe theſe neceſſary points thus ſummarily compriſed by our Church. And the truth is, ſince the people have had more knowledge than this, it hath made them (what it was objected to St. <hi>Paul</hi> his Learning had him) mad: I ſhould have ſaid, ſince they have had more, they have had leſs; for they have neglected a great deal of this, which was more neceſſary than what ſucceeded in its room.</p>
            <p>And yet how little a part is this, according to ſome, of the neceſſary Chriſtianity for the people? Not a word here of the <hi>eternal Decrees</hi> of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſome the great and neceſſary founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our happineſs. The reaſon poſſibly was, becauſe our Church thought it enough, as ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that part of the Creed, to believe the holy <hi>Catholick Church</hi> was the <hi>Elect people</hi> of God, or Gods choice people; but of thoſe without, ſhe thought the people ought to judge, no more than what ſhe ſaith, and that is nothing. Again, not a word here
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45271:13"/> of the <hi>holy Diſcipline,</hi> and what <hi>form,</hi> or if any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtrictly inſtituted by God; which if it were not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the peoples common Chriſtianity, ſome men abominably did, and ſtill do abuſe the World, who preach to them little elſe or more vehemently than invectives againſt Biſhops and Epiſcopacy. The reaſon why our Church paſs'd this point over ſo lightly, may be preſumed becauſe ſhe found a form of Government ſetled in the Catholick Church, which could pretend to more of a Divine Right than any elſe could be produced. And therefore what was enough for people to know, was what ſhe ſayes, that we ſhould <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to all our Governours,</hi> Teachers, Spiritual Paſtors and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. And of this point of Government, while they would know more, we ſee they unlearn thus much, they grow <hi>forgetful of this neceſſary.</hi> I may not inſiſt on more inſtances: by theſe it is evident, the too much <hi>enlarging</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrine, produceth the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>knowledge</hi> which we complain of.</p>
            <p>Again, there are <hi>various Gifts</hi> made very much neceſſary to Chriſtianity, or as they ſpeak to a gracious heart, which being not ſo neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the like effect, though people at firſt do not perceive it. I ſhall inſtance only in what they call the <hi>Gift of Prayer,</hi> which ſome can ſcarce think any perſon who hath received true Grace, in ſome meaſure at leaſt to want. A thing ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſſary to every private mans Chriſtianity, that in truth it can ſcarce be ſaid to have any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45271:14"/> and diſtinct nature at all. For if we will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand any thing of ſenſe thereby, its import is, a gift or <hi>faculty</hi> of <hi>utterance</hi> in the particular caſe, or office of Prayer; and ſo conſiſts in a <hi>readineſs</hi> of <hi>invention,</hi> and <hi>volubility</hi> of ſpeech: which whoſo has, and uſeth as much to other purpoſes, ſuppoſe to Preaching, as to Praying, would be equally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert at both, that is to ſay, have as good a gift of <hi>Preaching</hi> as of <hi>Praying.</hi> So that both being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially one and the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> a faculty of ready uttering what a man hath conceived, if there could be any ſuch diſtinct thing as the gift of Prayer, that gift of Prayer would be no more neceſſary to any one to make him a Chriſtian, than it would be to every Chriſtian that he have the gift of Preaching, becauſe I ſay the nature of both is <hi>one</hi> and the ſame. I cannot now digreſs to vindicate particular Texts, which giddy heads have detorted to aſſert this matter; but I only ſay, and appeal for truth thereof to ſad experience, that ſince pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, as thinking it neceſſary to their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, have made it their great buſineſs to make their Prayers as faſt as they ſay them, they have pickt up <hi>words</hi> and <hi>phraſes,</hi> and forgot and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected neceſſary things; they have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with their own dreams and rambles, and miſtaken commotions of wild <hi>fancy</hi> and <hi>affection,</hi> for the ſolid <hi>joys,</hi> and Chriſtian comfort, which only ariſe from the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, that is, from a reflexion on a virtuous life. In
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45271:14"/> ſhort, as men ought not to be <hi>idle,</hi> and neglect the improving of their underſtanding in ſearching into commonly reputed truths, or raiſing their other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of utterance in whatever caſes may benefit themſelves or others, ſo ought all firſt to make <hi>ſure</hi> of ſuch <hi>neceſſaries</hi> as before ſpoken of, leſt while they ſpend their time on what they might have ſpared, they periſh for the lack of knowledge of what ſurely would have made them happy.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſecond</hi> original of this deſtructive ignorance amongſt us, I conceive to be the <hi>miſtaking</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>ſincerity,</hi> or what it is heartily to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian or Convert. Many poor honeſt-minded per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, have ſuppos'd it to be little elſe, than to be <hi>zealouſly</hi> addicted to that <hi>Party</hi> or Faction, which of all others they judged <hi>pureſt.</hi> You'l ſay, ſuch were ſilly, or Fools<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And who can help it, if many have been made ſuch? Let their Seducers anſwer for that. Again, Others, of more ſobriety and good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have thought ſincerity to be nothing elſe but the <hi>motion</hi> of good <hi>affections</hi> in holy Exerciſes: When they have pray'd or heard with ſome <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedneſs</hi> under each part of the office, their breaſts relenting, and as it were thawing from their an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient ſenceleſneſs; by reaſon of a more attentive temper at ſuch times than others, they have thought this to be indubitable ſincerity. Not conſidering that even a <hi>Romance,</hi> a well contriv'd and well <hi>acted Play,</hi> in an attentive Auditor, ſhall beget like <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments</hi> of grief, hope, commiſeration, joy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45271:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> And having run away with this miſtake, whatever it was, which they remembred to have raiſed their affections, and begot in them ſuch inward titilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of griefs, hopes or joys, this they conceived they ought to make it their whole buſineſs to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And becauſe <hi>Novelty</hi> had this effect, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if ſet up (as was the cuſtom) with ſome <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick geſtures</hi> and <hi>tones,</hi> therefore they could hear Sermons and long-winded Prayers all their days. Nor were they concerned either to underſtand or remember them, much leſs to practice them. It was enough if they were <hi>moved</hi> and wrought upon by the preſent, hearing of them, though they came back again no whit the wiſer, nor a jot more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on any particular Duty, or againſt ſin. I am far from cenſuring all late Non-Conformiſts of this weakneſs: but the event ſhews it to have been good in many, who will ſay they have wondrouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by ſuch a Sermon, of which they are not able to tell you two words. The poor people do not <hi>diſſemble,</hi> but are <hi>deceived:</hi> They mean their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were tickled and ſtirred by it. Hence it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, ſuch perſons neſtle themſelves up in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and whereas <hi>ſincerity</hi> lies in an <hi>heart ſoberly changed,</hi> and a <hi>virtuous life</hi> flowing from thence, this they overlook, and ſeeing not, run on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, till many times they periſh for lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>A <hi>third</hi> thing, which becauſe it will be eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood a cauſe of this miſchief, we need but touch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45271:15"/> upon, is ſome mens <hi>pride</hi> and ſelf conceit. As they are confident they are Saints and ſhall be ſaved, whereas the reprobate World they are ſure ſhall periſh, ſo have they the ſame good confidence that they have Saving knowledge, and a more Spiritual notion of Divine Truths than other people, who cannot but be carnal, becauſe they talk ſo much of reaſon, and endeavour both to apprehend and teach Chriſtianity, ſo as to make ſenſe of it, and give a reaſon for it: And what marvel if ſuch who are ignorant or miſtaken, and will not learn, periſh by a deſtructive ignorance?</p>
            <p>A <hi>fourth</hi> evil, which will be eaſily apprehended to be of the ſame malign influence, is the <hi>admiration</hi> of ſome mens <hi>perſons.</hi> There have been men whoſe buſineſs it has been to make themſelves <hi>popular,</hi> to the end they might have power to overturn what they did not like. Theſe have ſcrewed themſelves into a good eſteem among common people, by crying out againſt the evils of the Times, the crimes of Great ones and Governours, (things which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are always greedy to hear of) and by an oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thoſe parts, which they had in an odd way from other men, have gained the repute of wiſe, and able, and holy: which advantage when they were ſenſible they had got, they then lead the people whither they pleaſed, as they ſaw themſelves able. And having brought a multitude to this paſs, that they would hear none but them, the poor people knew little more than what they would let them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45271:16"/> know, and thoſe were moſtly ſuch curioſities and whimſies as ſpoken of, which did confound, not edifie unto ſalvation.</p>
            <p>A <hi>fifth</hi> original of this lack of ſober knowledge, is a <hi>barbarous conſtancy</hi> to mens own <hi>Opinions,</hi> though too <hi>raſhly</hi> by them taken up. The moſt men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to have been miſtaken: and when they ſee their error, confeſs it not to be ſuch, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make it probable, till they have even cheated themſelves and believe their own deluſion. And then beſides that theſe opinions, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of them, take up the time and thought, which ſober knowledge ought to do, Errors hanging as in a ſtring, and one part drawing on the other, they cannot believe, at leaſt not maintain one, but they muſt admit more. And ſo in fine the ſober know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge becomes partly adulterated, partly neglected and oppreſs'd, and men periſh through deſtructive ignorance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>laſt</hi> of theſe banefull miſchiefs which I ſhall preſent, is the <hi>holding the truth in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Men ſometimes are not ignorant, and yet become ſo. They do know Truth, and their Duty, but they have no mind ſuch things ſhould be Truths, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then ſuch and ſuch points muſt be Duty. They <hi>ſtudy</hi> therefore what <hi>uncertainty</hi> they can find in thoſe ungrateful Truths, and after-long ſearch, ſometimes think they have found a knot in the Bulruſh. They then <hi>doubt</hi> what before they ſaw evidence to believe: after proceed to <hi>impugn,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45271:16"/> in the end totally <hi>diſ-believe.</hi> By this means come multitudes to periſh for want of ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which acquieſces in the due evidence of Truths.</p>
            <p>But what redreſs can be found for this deſtructive wanr of ſober Divine knowledge?</p>
            <p>The <hi>remedies</hi> are either <hi>publick</hi> or <hi>private.</hi> I begin with the private, which I commend to every mans Conſcience in the fear of God, as by a ſtrict ſcrutiny thereof he finds himſelf more or leſs to ſeek, either in underſtanding the notions, or ſeeking the evidence of Divine Truths.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> will be, to <hi>reſolve</hi> upon a ſpirit of <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> and thoſe which are by her ſent, as able to inſtruct them in the Lord. It is beyond all controverſie, and confeſs'd by our Adverſaries, that all thoſe things which are <hi>neceſſary</hi> to our ſalvation, are certainly <hi>determined</hi> by our Church. As to thoſe things which are more uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and indifferent, and ſo apt to ingenerate ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, no man of <hi>modeſty</hi> or good manners but muſt ſay, they are likely to be beſt determined by Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors. And it is undoubted, that our Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Governors and Paſtors in his Church, and that when he promiſed to be with them unto the end of the world, he aſſur'd us too they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end of the world. And when that command (and the like) was given, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you in the Lord, and ſubmit your ſelves,</hi> it was intended to oblige unto the end of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45271:17"/> the world: wherefore I ſee not how men can doubt but that they are indiſpenſible bound by the Law of God to what I adviſe. And one would think what I adviſe is ſo reaſonable, that it ſhould eaſily take. For what is it in effect, but to deſire common people to have the <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>civility</hi> to their <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and thoſe Reverend <hi>Convocation,</hi> which have laboured in the modelling the Doctrine and Orders of our Church, according to Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive patterns, to believe them neither to have been <hi>Knaves</hi> nor <hi>Fools:</hi> to have underſtood better than a company of pragmatical Novelliſts, (many of whom ſcarce ever read over three good Books in their lives, beſides the Bible) what was Chriſtian, and Primitive, and neceſſary: and then not to have gone about to abuſe their power and truſt, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding contrary to their knowledge, to ruine their own ſouls and other mens. Truly I cannot ſee how any common private perſon can adhere to his own Judgment, againſt this the publick Judgment of his Governors, but he muſt think the one of theſe of them, at leaſt that they are ſuch comparatively in reſpect of himſelf. Wherefore in ſhort, let us be content to <hi>learn</hi> Chriſtianity, as to its neceſſary part, from our Church, which in the Catechiſm, Prayer-Book and Homilies, all even the darkeſt places have opportunities to do, and in moſt places, God be bleſſed, other plentiful advantages beſides. And as to us who are <hi>Miniſters,</hi> let us carefully <hi>teach</hi> according to this form of Doctrine, leſt we come to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45271:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> have charged upon us not only Error and Schiſm, but alſo Apoſtacy, if not Perjury. This will be one more private remedy of the want of neceſſary knowledge.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſecond</hi> will be, that people would endeavour, when converſant in the publick worſhip of God, to <hi>hear with underſtanding:</hi> I mean, would not only <hi>attend</hi> unto the <hi>words</hi> and forms of ſpeech which they hear, but to the <hi>things,</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to carry them with them treaſured up in faithful minds. It's poſſible every plain man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not every word, or if he did, could not remember the hundredth part: yet the drift, ſcope and common ſubject of all, repreſented in ſo various forms, few attentive perſons can miſs. As for inſtance: ſuppoſe me to have heard a diſcourſe of Repentance; poſſible all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives to it, and particular rules in its practice, I may not ſo diſtinctly conceive or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: but thus much, that without Repentance no forgiveneſs of ſin is to be had, and that every ſorrow for ſin is not Repentance, but it muſt be a durable Reformation which only will paſs with God; this I may eaſily retain. And ſo much as this ſhould a perſon definent in ſober knowledge learn by each Sermon, truly he would not be long in danger of periſhing by any deſtructive ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let each perſon conſcientiouſly cleave
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45271:18"/> unto, and <hi>practice</hi> what he underſtands, and hath ſufficient evidence to perſwade him is his concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What we have above ſaid of Errors, is no leſs certain of all Chriſtian Truths and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; they have a moſt neceſſary connexion, and one will draw in another. He that adheres to one Truth, will by force and conſequence of that be lead into more. He that practiſeth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his common dealings with man, will at length ſee he muſt give <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> as well as pay <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> the money he owes them; that is, be a Loyal as well as an Honeſt man. Beſides, ſuch may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the bleſſing and influence of Heaven to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour their weakneſs: for <hi>the ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let ſuch an one <hi>beware</hi> of all thoſe <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recited</hi> evils, which induce an ignorance of plain neceſſaries. Let him be content his Faith be no larger than the Churches. Let him place ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in an honeſt heart, and conſcientious practice. Let him beware of pride, ſelf-conceit, and being led by the noſe by men diſſenting from publick determinations, and of popular and moving hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Let him never be aſhamed to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and renounce his error, or to amend his fault, and in nothing let him live againſt the ſolid rational dictates of his Conſcience. Solid
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45271:18"/> rational dictates, I ſaid, for in matters of plain neceſſity, Conſcience will quickly be reſolved: and in ſcruples touching leſſer matters, I am of the mind clearly, without any other difficult rules, every common man ought to <hi>ſubmit</hi> his Judgment to his <hi>Spiritual Guides,</hi> and they theirs to the <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> and that is a ſhort iſſue, and we may quickly live ſober, honeſt, and in peace; and I think then we are <hi>wiſe</hi> enough <hi>unto ſalvation,</hi> that is, paſt the danger of being <hi>deſtroyed for lack of knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains I ſhould now ſpeak to the <hi>publick</hi> remedies: but theſe, according to the purport of my former Doctrine, I <hi>leave</hi> to my <hi>Superiors,</hi> whom they concern, and whom I pretend not to inſtruct, as being always reſolved, according to my Duty, to believe them wiſer than my ſelf, and better to underſtand the redreſs of publick evils. I will therefore briefly conclude the whole, in an earneſt <hi>addreſs</hi> to perſons of all conditions, that they will each <hi>endeavour</hi> by the moſt proper means they have heard, or can deviſe, to ſecure to themſelves, and propagate amongſt others, this <hi>practical knowledge,</hi> a knowledge which may make them and the World more pure, more peaceable, full of all good works, without partiality and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>My Brethren, we all of us profeſs to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that is, perſons who believe our ſelves to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45271:19"/> have here <hi>no abiding place,</hi> but to <hi>ſeek one to come, a City which has foundations whoſe builder and maker is God;</hi> this World therefore to be a place which we muſt only paſs through, but yet that we ought ſo to demean our ſelves in our paſſage, as to ſecure a bliſsful reception at our journeys end: If this be our belief, as it is our pretence, there can be but <hi>two</hi> things, as to our Souls, of concernment to us: the firſt, <hi>to know</hi> what may make us virtuous; the ſecond, to <hi>be virtuous</hi> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of what we know. It is the firſt of theſe which my whole diſcourſe hath driven at, yet ſo that in all likelihood, that attain'd will ſecure the latter.</p>
            <p>And I beſeech you give me leave a little to expoſtulate the caſe: What have theſe glorious, theſe Heaven-born Souls of ours deſerved of us, that they ſhould be made ſlaves and vaſſals to what is baſe or mean? that they ſhould be rais'd and imployed to no better offices, than to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how to <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> well, or how to amaſs <hi>thick clay,</hi> or get money, it may be to <hi>put it into a bag with holes?</hi> Or if we think knowledge an acquiſt more worthy of them, why then ſhould they be airy and trivial notions only which we will purſue? Why not this <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> which is both of preſent and eternal <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>excellence;</hi> which will transform us into the Divine likeneſs here in Virtue, and hereafter in Glory.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45271:19"/>
            <p>Sure it is, we cannot but approve this kind of knowledge as <hi>fitteſt</hi> for us, and of all moſt <hi>honourable,</hi> and which may moſt truly denominate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us knowing. For all wiſe men judge him to be the moſt Learned, who underſtands not ſo much variety of things, as that one thing, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him and which he profeſſes. Now as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians what concerns us more, or what profeſs we more than Holineſs?</p>
            <p>Then, if we look to the effects of this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it is really moſt <hi>Pleaſant,</hi> as conducing to poſſeſs us of clean and quiet breaſts, the <hi>greateſt</hi> pleaſure on earth, and much the moſt <hi>noble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, we cannot be unſenſible of thoſe moſt effectual means and <hi>advantages,</hi> which we have hereto, if we will not be wanting to our ſelves; God having <hi>revealed</hi> the Doctrine hereof from Heaven, and that by his Son ſent into the world to <hi>enlighten every man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As we would not then be deſtroyed everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, by our own ſelves too, and that moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſably, let us <hi>meditate</hi> in theſe things <hi>day and night;</hi> Let the <hi>knowledge of the Holy,</hi> the rule of Virtue, and articles and evidences of Faith, which are all ſo many incentives to the moſt ſtrictly virtuous life, be our greateſt ſtudy. We ſhall thus ſurely eſcape this danger of periſhing for <hi>lack of knowledge:</hi> and then there can be but one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45271:20"/> danger only remaining, and that is of periſhing for lack of <hi>practice;</hi> which too certainly we ſhall eſcape, if we ſuffer ſuch knowledge to have its perfect work upon us.</p>
            <closer>Which that we may do, the Lord grant us his grace, and by that bring us to glory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: To whom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45271:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
